<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Vuizur's blog - Language Learning</title><link href="https://vuizur.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://vuizur.github.io/blog/feeds/language-learning.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://vuizur.github.io/blog/</id><updated>2022-10-16T12:44:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>How to learn Czech</title><link href="https://vuizur.github.io/blog/how-to-learn-czech.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-10-16T12:44:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-16T12:44:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Vuizur</name></author><id>tag:vuizur.github.io,2022-10-16:/blog/how-to-learn-czech.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Learning Czech isn't super easy. Not many people speak it, and only a few resources exist. Here is what I found to be useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The absolute beginning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you need to learn the alphabet. It's not that hard, but there are some differences to English. You can find an alright …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Learning Czech isn't super easy. Not many people speak it, and only a few resources exist. Here is what I found to be useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The absolute beginning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you need to learn the alphabet. It's not that hard, but there are some differences to English. You can find an alright overview of the alphabet &lt;a href="https://www.omniglot.com/writing/czech.htm"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, especially the linked video is useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For getting basic vocabulary and a general feel for the language, I recommend using Anki. I made a deck generator that can be used to make a Czech-English (or Czech-German/Spanish/...) deck &lt;a href="https://github.com/Vuizur/tatoeba-to-anki"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Intermediate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For practicing listening, my favourite is the podcast &lt;a href="https://cesky.buzzsprout.com/"&gt;Čeština s Michalem&lt;/a&gt;. The host has a very clear pronunciation, and it is easy to follow. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also recommend practicing reading once you're ready. If you want to read ebooks, I like to use the Czech dictionary integrated in KOReader (which I also created :)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For practicing writing, I can recommend a chatbot, for example my (of course) bot &lt;a href="https://vuizur.github.io/react-gpt3-chatbot/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. (Requires an OpenAI key, but creating an account will give you free credits.) You only need to set a Czech prompt in the settings like "Rozhovor mezi mužem a ženou." The bot is not as smart as in other languages, but I think it is still the most intelligent Czech chatbot out there and will only get better as OpenAI improves their models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Advanced&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would simply recommend reading more books. And talking to people, either with language exchange sites or https://www.free4talk.com/ (if you are very lucky). Another choice is buying Italki lessons. You can also try a conversation topics generator like &lt;a href="https://vuizur.github.io/conversation-topics/"&gt;the one here&lt;/a&gt; and simply hold monologues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you should watch movies/Youtube videos/series in Czech. I cannot recommend anything here, because tastes differ, but there is a lot, for example on Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Language Learning"></category><category term="Czech"></category><category term="Resources"></category></entry></feed>